Guide to the Edward Comfort Starr Collection 1864-1927 MS002 MS002 MS002
Cornwall Historical Society
Edward Comfort Starr Collection
1864-1927
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS002
1.5 linear feet 3 boxes
This collection contains the personal items of Cornwall minister and historian, Edward Comfort Starr (1844-1941).Starr was born in Guilford, Connecticut on January 12, 1844 to John and Lydia Starr. As a pastor at Cornwall’s First Church, Starr took a special interest in the community’s history.
Provenance
Donated by Edward Comfort Starr.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
This collection contains the personal items of Cornwall minister and historian, Edward Comfort Starr (1844-1941).Starr was born in Guilford, Connecticut on January 12, 1844 to John and Lydia Starr. In 1866, Starr graduated from Yale College, and three years later graduated from Yale Seminary. As a Congregationalist minister, Starr was formally ordained in Waseca, Minnesota in 1871, and served the Congregationalist church there for five years before removing to the Wethersfield Avenue Church in Hartford. While working in Hartford, Starr married Emily Amelia Shew in 1878, and the couple ultimately had three children, Charles, Edward, and Mabel. In 1881, due to health reasons, Starr was transferred to the community of Northfield, Connecticut, where he preached for six years before being reassigned to Cornwall in 1888.
Scope and Content Note
As a pastor at Cornwall’s First Church, Starr took a special interest in the community’s history.A prolific researcher and writer, Starr collected hundreds of items related to Cornwall’s past, ultimately culminating in the 1926 publication of his book, A History of Cornwall, Connecticut: A Typical New England Town. Starr’s personal items later formed the basis for the Cornwall Historical Society’s collections. Starr served the First Church until 1915, and remained in the community following his resignation. Following his death on January 16, 1941, his collections were given to the Cornwall Library, and were transferred to the Cornwall Historical Society upon its incorporation in 1964.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Personal Papers
Cornwall History
Research Notes
Dairy farming--Connecticut.; Conrwall (Conn.)--history.; Correspondence; Research Notes; Booklets; Photographs; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Starr Family; Cornwall (Conn.)--history.
- Personal Papers
  - Church Matters
    - Booklet, "Plan of Christian Work", 1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notice for donations for the building of a new chapel, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Annual First Congregational Church circular letter, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Report of annual First Church meeting, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bill for gift of brass rail given to First Church, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Christmas lesson and accompanying responsive reading, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Constitution and by-laws of Litchfield Northwest Association of Churches, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Floral committee notecard, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Outline Life of Christ, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Private circular letter for members of the Waseca Congregational Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Schedule of church work at Waseca Congregational Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Program for Wethersfield Avenue Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sunday school teacher’s meeting exercises form, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Timeline of the Apostolic Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personal Items
    - Songbook of the Pleonia Society, listing songs sung by Starr, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Program for Memorial Day exercises in memory of John Sedgwick, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Report card of Edward B. Starr, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from E.A. Hill, about his family, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Note inviting E.C. Starr to concert in Norfolk, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from C.L. Gold, with suggested new Cornwall place-names, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from V.C. Beers, about Cornwall place-names, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from Vanderbilt University librarian, regarding church conference meeting minutes, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from Benjamin Sedgwick, regarding Cornwall cemeteries, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Empty envelope, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Invitation to Starr family reunion, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Photographs
    - Photo of E.C. Starr, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Photo of E.C. Starr, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Writings
    - Articles on local history, 1893-1928; , undated (Box 1, Folder 28-38)
    - Religious publications, 1879-1909; , undated (Box 1, Folder 39-55)
    - Article on Pleonia Society memories, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Poem, “The Sunset Gun,” for Yale Class of 1866 reunion, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Cornwall History
  - Research notes for A History of Cornwall, Connecticut
    - Cornwall Chorus, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Cornwall proprietors, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cornwall Red Cross, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Cornwall Village Improvement Society, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Debating clubs, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Holiday observances, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Law and Order League, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Minerals, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Musical matters, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - New England weather, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Post offices, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Railroads and stage coaches, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Soldiers, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Telegraph, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Telephone, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - “Traditional Tales” of Cornwall, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Literary people of Cornwall, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Reviews of A History of Cornwall, Connecticut
    - Review in The Missionary Herald, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Review by H.S. Canby is The Saturday Review of Literature, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Review in the New York Herald Tribune, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Notes on Baptist ministers not included in Starr’s History
    - Silas Ambler, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - G.B. Atwell, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - W.D. Baldwin, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - John P. Barnett, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Virgil W. Blackman, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Augusts C. Engeline, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - S. Gale, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - C.J. Gordon, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - J.F. Jones, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Cornelius E. Malley, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - B.F. Nye, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Charles L. Owens, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - George F. Ray, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Levi Peck, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Daniel Robinson, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - J. F. Smith, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Samuel J. Smith, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - A.H. Stock, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - C.Y. Swan, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Richard Thompson, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Walter B. Vassar, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - A.D. Watrous, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - L.W. Wheeler, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Envelope formerly containing notes on Baptist ministers, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Notes on miscellaneous men not mentioned in Starr’s History
    - Marie LeBaron Andrews, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - William Given Andrews, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - J.J. Averill, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - H. Baerman, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Jacob A. Biddle, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Ebenezer Bishop, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - C.L. Blake, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Edwin D. Bowers, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Charles S. Brower, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Erastus Cole, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - J.H. Doughty and J.A. Drown, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - William H. Guernsey, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - E. Hale, F.W. Hall, and T. Hall, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Elias Hart, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Elias Burton Hart, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - George S. Hart, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Hezekiah M. Hart, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Jessie Osborne Hart, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Nathan Hart, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Phineas Hart, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Thomas Hodge, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Dr. Hollister, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Palmer Hopkins, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Amos Johnson, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Solomon Johnson, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Anastasius Karavelles, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - E.H. Mullineaux, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - J.T. Norton and Ozias Palmer, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - A.F. Palmer, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Miles A. Pond, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - J.D. Potter, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Charles A. Rider, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Francis L. Robbins, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Bennett Roberts, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - C.H. Smith, undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - C.L.P. Smith, undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - A. Somers and W. Spaulding, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - William F. Swift, undated (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - James P. Woodruff, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Envelope formerly containing notes on miscellaneous men, undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
- Research Notes
  - Anamis Ackerly, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Charles R. Adams, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - William R. Agate, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fredus Aldridge, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Luman Andrews, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Eli Barnett, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - F.V. Bartley, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Benjamin Beach, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - H.H. Birkins, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Truman Bishop, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Moses Blydenburg, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - James D. Bouton, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Edward L. Bray, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Brayton, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Wesley Budd, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - James Campbell, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Ezekiel Canfield, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Milo chamberlain, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Laban C. Cheney, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Laban Clark, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sylvester H. Clark, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Samuel Cochrane, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Robert Codling, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Jonathan N. Crane, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Cyrus Culver, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - W.M. Curtis, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Smith Dayton, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Daniel Dennis, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - C.L. Dickeman, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Francis Donelly, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Harry Eames, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Thomas Edwards, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Thomas Ellis, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - N. Emery and D. Ensign, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Julius Field, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - W.J. Gilbert and B.A. Gilman, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Lewis Gunn, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Frank M. Hallock, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Reuben Harris, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Billy Hibbard, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Gilbert Hubbell, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Elisha P. Jacob, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Augustus Jocelyn, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Samuel F. Johnson, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Horace Judd, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - R. Kirby and A. Knell, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Samuel W. Law, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Charles W. Lockwood, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - D. Lounsbury and J. Lovejoy, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - J. Luckey and J. Lyon, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Zalmon Lyon, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - David L. Marks, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Joseph D. Marshall, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - John J. Matthais, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Alexander McAllister, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Luther Mead, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - David Miller, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Joseph Mitchel, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Peter Moriarty, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Caleb Morris, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - David Nash, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - John Nixon, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - David Osborn, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Elbert Osborn, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Charles F. Pelton, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Smith H. Platt, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Andrew Prindle, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - John Reynolds, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - James Robinson, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - William Ross, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Luman A. Sanford, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Arnold Scofield, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Bradley Sillick, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - A.E. Smith, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Eben Smith, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - James Smith and Joseph Smith, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Lemuel Smith, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Samuel W. Smith, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Sylvester Smith, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Revis H. Stebbins and A.E. Steinbridge, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - David S. Stevens, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Ebenezer Stevens, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - John K. Still, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Davis Stocking, undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - J. Stoneman, G. Stott, and L. Stowe, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Matthais Swain, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - W. Swayze and J. Sweet, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - William Thatcher, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Thomas Thorpe, undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Philip Wager, undated (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - William Wake, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Ebenezer Washburn, undated (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Samuel Weeks, undated (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Jason Wells, undated (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - A.G. Wickwire and S. Wigton, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Wells Wolcott, undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Timothy C. Youngs, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Envelope formerly containing contents of Methodist ministers not included in Starr’s Histor, undated (Box 3, Folder 98)